Guide to the Boris Filippov Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Boris Filippov papers
1908-1969
GEN MSS 334
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.55
(21 boxes)
The papers consist of Filippov's correspondence with Russian émigré literary figures and scholars, typescripts of Filippov's writings (poetry, prose, critical essays), materials for works edited by Filippov as well as writings by others not included in works edited by Filippov; and artwork by Serge Hollerbach for books edited by Filippov.
Filippov, Boris, 1905-1991
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Boris Filippov, 1969.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Restricted Fragile Papers in Box 21 may only be consulted with permission of the appropriate curator. Preservation photocopies have been substituted in the main files for general reference use.
BORIS FILIPPOV (1905-1991)
Boris Filippov was born Boris Andreevich Filistinskii in Stavropol', in the Caucasus, on 6 August 1905. In the early 1920s, Filippov was active in experimental schools and educational societies, under the tutelage of accomplished scholars. Filippov later credited one of these, the philosopher Sergei TSvetkov, with having had the greatest impact on his own thought.
Filippov received his post-secondary education first at the Leningrad Institute of Modern Oriental Languages (1924-28), and then at the Evening Institute of Industrial Construction (1928-33). He became an accountant in this field and then worked as an instructor (Dozent). Throughout this period Filippov was an active participant in religious-philosophical circles in Leningrad; in 1925 he organized a group under the leadership of philosopher Sergei Askol'dov. Filippov's career as a architectural engineer, however, was hampered by a series of arrests for tied to his membership in unofficial associations. His first arrest occurred in spring of 1927. A subsequent arrest led to his incarceration in remote labor camps from 1936-41.
Upon his release in 1941, Filippov was exiled to Novgorod, where he was reunited with Sergei Askol'dov, and also met such prominent pre-revolutionary figures as Tat'iana and Natal'ia Gippius, sisters of the Symbolist poet Zinaida Gippius. When the invading German army occupied Novgorod soon thereafter, Filippov, Askol'dov and other exiled intellectuals took an active part in city administration and published in pro-Nazi Russian-language publications. His actions, perceived by some as collaboration, became a source of controversy in the post-war years. In 1943 Filippov followed the retreating Germans to Pskov, Riga, and then on to Germany, where he lived for a time in a displaced persons' camp near Munich. At this time he was married to the poet Irina Bushman.
In 1950 Filippov moved to New York, marrying Ol'ga Anstei in 1951. When this marriage failed in 1954 Filippov settled in Washington D. C., where he remained for the rest of his life. He divorced Ol'ga Anstei in 1965. Soon thereafter he married Evgeniia Vladimirovna Zhiglevich, who became a partner in his publishing enterprises. Boris Filippov died in Washington, D.C. on May 3, 1991.
Filippov's first known publications were in Russian-language newspapers under Nazi occupation. After the war, while living in a DP camp near Munich, Filippov became co-editor of the literary and political journal Grani and contributed to other émigré publications. After moving to the United States, Filippov continued to write poetry, stories and critical articles, which were collected into a series of books, including: Kresty i perekrestki (1957) Veter Skifii (1959), Nepogod' (1960), Skvoz' tuchi (1960), Bremia vremeni (1961), Pyl'noe solntse (1961), Polustanki (1962), Rubezhi (1962), Muzykal'naia shkatulka (1963), Stynushchaia vechnost' (1964), Kochev'ia (1964), Zhivoe proshloe (1965), Tuskloe okontse (1967) and Veter svezheet (1969). He also worked on a freelance basis as a construction consultant and researcher of Soviet architecture.
Gradually, however, Filippov's own career as a writer was overshadowed by his tireless editorial and publishing activity. Beginning with the 1961 collection Sovetskaia potaennaia muza, Filippov set about making available the works of writers who could not be published in the Soviet Union, from Dostoevsky's "U Tikhona," omitted from the novel Besy ( Demons ), to the poetry of Silver Age poets and émigré literature. To this purpose, Filippov founded the Inter-Language Literary Associates, which used money from cultural organizations such as the Tower Foundation to arrange the publication, under varying auspices, of this wide range of literature. Together with Gleb Struve, professor of Russian literature at the University of California-Berkeley, Filippov edited and published the collected works of Anna Akhmatova, Nikolai Gumilev, Nikolai Kliuev, Osip Mandel'shtam, Boris Pasternak, Maksimilian Voloshin, and Nikolai Zabolotskii. It was in part due to Filippov's initiative that similar editions of Viacheslav Ivanov and Evgenii Zamiatin also appeared in the 1970s. Filippov was instrumental in publishing the works of the Soviet dissidents IUlii Daniel' (pseudonym: Nikolai Arzhak) and Andrei Siniavskii (pseudonym: Abram Terts), whose 1965 trial is well documented in Filippov's papers and correspondence.
In 1968 Filippov came under intense criticism by Soviet publications and some émigré groups for his anti-Soviet activities, which were tied to his wartime collaboration with the Germans. It was hinted that Filippov's publications were funded by the CIA, USIA, or other US intelligence organizations. At the close of 1968, Filippov resigned his directorship of Inter-Language Literary Associates, ostensibly to deflect undue attention from its contributions to the anti-Soviet cause. The publishing house promptly fell into neglect. Thereafter, he continued his writing, editing and publishing with the London-based Overseas Publications Interchange.
For Filippov's account of his childhood and episodes of his later life, see his memoirs, Vsplyvshee v pamiati (London: Overseas Publications Interchange Ltd., 1990.) For a detailed listing of works issued with Filippov's participation, either as author, editor or introducer, see Vsplyvshee v pamiati (385-9).
Scope and Contents
The Boris Filippov Papers, 1908-1969 (bulk 1944-1969), contains correspondence and writings of Boris Filippov, as well as project files for books he edited, writings by others, and book cover art by Serge Hollerbach for a number of Filippov editions. The collection is housed in 21 boxes and comprises 8.55 linear feet of material.
The organization of the archive largely follows that established by Filippov himself. Manuscripts of works published by Filippov can be found both in Series III, Books edited by B. A. Filippov and Series I, Correspondence, where some manuscripts were interfiled with Filippov's correspondence with the authors or their representatives.
Series I, Correspondence, 1946-1969, (Boxes 1-10) includes Filippov's business and personal correspondence with a wide range of literary and cultural figures. Principal correspondents include: Georgii Adamovich, Lidiia Alekseeva, IUrii Annenkov, Ivan Bashkirtsev (proprietor of Baschkirzew Buchdruckerei), Nina Berberova, Clarence Brown, Igor' Chinnov, Jozef Czapski, Tat'iana Fedorova (Rannit), Tat'iana and Victor Frank, Jerzy Giedroyc (of Institut Littéraire), Grani, Johannes von Guenther, Serge Hollerbach, IUrii Ivask, Archbishop Ioann (Shakhovskoi), Nina Kandinsky (the widow of Wassily Kandinsky), Dmitrii I. Klenovskii, Vera and Lydia Kovarsky, Serge Lifar, Boris Nartsissov, Rostislav Pletnev, Emmanuil Rais, Aleksis Rannit, G. Rosimov IUrii Ofrosimov), Leonid Denisovich Rzhevskii, Vladimir Samarin, Princess Zinaida Schakovskoy (and La pensée russe ), Ol'ga Shor (literary executor of V. I. Ivanov), Heinrich Stammler, Aleksei Struve, Gleb Struve, N. A. Struve, IUrii Terapiano, Marie Under, and Boris Zaitsev. Other correspondents of note include Roman Gul', Vladimir and Vera Nabokov, Dimitri Obolensky, and Vladimir Veidle.
Series II, Writings by B. A. Filippov, 1944-68, (Boxes 11-12) comprises full or partial typescripts of several of his books, including Tuskloe okontse, Veter svezheet, Vsegda sovremenniki: literturnye ocherki, and Vstrechnye v doroge and of shorter works, including poems and short stories.
Series III, Books edited by B. A. Filippov, 1908-67 (Boxes 13-17) includes preparatory matter, typescripts and page proofs of books that Filippov edited or published. Included here are manuscripts of introductory material or commentary by Filippov, IUrii Ivask, Emmanuil Rais and Vera von Wiren-Garczynski. Authors whose books are represented in the files include: Anna Akhmatova, Maria Under, Nikolai Danilevskii, Nikolai Gumilev, Wassily Kandinsky, Nikolai Kliuev, Osip Mandel'shtam, Abram Terts (pseudonym of Andrei Siniavskii), and Mikhail Zoshchenko.
Series IV, Writings of Others, 1927-67 (Boxes 18-19) includes stories, poems and articles written by Filippov's colleagues or friends which, as far as is known, did not appear under his editorship. Included here are stories by Filippov's friend Leonid Bogdanov, and also the page proofs of Svet v nochi by Georgii Meier.
Series V, Book-Cover Art by Serge Hollerbach, 1965-66 (Box 20) contains sketches and mock-ups of book covers for Filippov's editions.
Authors, Russian -- 20th Century -- Archives; Authors, Russian -- 20th Century; Russian literature -- 20th Century; Adamovich, Georgiĭ, 1892-1972; Alekseeva, Lidii︠a︡, 1909-1989; Annenkov, I͡Uriĭ, 1889-1974; Filippov, Boris, 1905-1991; Guenther, Johannes von, 1886-1973; Hollerbach, Serge, 1923-; Ivask, I︠U︡riĭ, 1907-1986; Kandinsky, Wassily, 1866-1944; Rannit, Aleksis; Rzhevskiĭ, Leonid, 1905-1986; Struve, Gleb, 1898-1985; Terapiano, I︠U︡riĭ, 1892-1980; Tert︠s︡, Abram, 1925-1997; Under, Marie, 1883-1980
- Correspondence, 1946-1969; I,; 4; (10 boxes)
  - "A" General, 1962-69 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adamovich, Georgii, 1964-69 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes: corrected typescript and corrected proofs (1967) of Edinstvo
  - Adson, A. I., 1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alekseeva, Lidiia, 1956-69, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
    [Pseudonym of L. A. Ivannikova]
  - Amosov, IU., 1956-65 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Andreev, Gennadii, 1960-69 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    [Pseudonym of Gennadii Andreevich Khomiakov]
  - Andreevskii, I. M., 1968-69 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Anisimov, Oleg, 1962 Dec 12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Annenkov, IUrii, 1964-67 (Box 1, Folder 13-17)
    Includes: holographs and typescript drafts of Dnevnik moikh vstrech, and a book-jacket sketch
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also: Box 20, folder 528
  - Arbuzov, E. L., 1956-69, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Argus, 1965-69 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    [Pseudonym of M. K. Aizenshtadt]
  - Aronson, G. IA., 1961-64 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "B" General, 1956-69 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Babitsky, Paul, 1967-69 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bashkirtsev, Ivan Ivanovich, 1959-69 (Box 1, Folder 23-30)
    Includes: Einheit Buchdruckerei, Baschkirzew Buchdruckerei, I. A. Los' Includes: letters from A. M. Mil'rud, Münchner Industriebuchbunderei Urban Meister, A. Neimanis, and De Donato editore "Leonardo da Vinci"
  - Bastunov, V. I., 1966-69, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bastunova, E. I. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Belinkov, A. V., 1968-69, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Belinkova, N. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Belopol'skii, A., 1966 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    [Also spelled Bielopole]
    Includes: Seiatel'
  - Berberova, Nina Nikolaevna, 1958-68 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Berkovich, L., 1967-68 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    [Also spelled Bercovicz]
    Includes Sofiia Galyshova
  - Bird, Christopher, 1960-63 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Includes: letters to Max Hayward, Gleb Struve, and Oliver Swan
  - Blums, Alberts, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Bol'shukhin, IU. IA., 1963-69 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bondarenko, Vladimir Ivanovich, 1957-69, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    [Also known as Walter Bond]
  - Books Abroad, 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    See also: Robert Vlach
  - Brown, Clarence, 1960-69 (Box 2, Folder 41-42)
    See also: Box 16, folder 427
  - Burkin, I. A., 1961-69 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Butkov, V., 1966-69 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - "C" General, 1963-64 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Chaplinskii, Ivan, 1966, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
    Includes: holograph "Otvet iz 4-kh glav: Prorocheskii otvet na telegrammu poslannuiu L. Dzhonsonu Vostochno- amerikanskoi eparkhii [sic] Pravoslavnykh episkopov vo glave Mitropolita Filareta."
  - Chinnov, Igor', 1966-69 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Criqui, Michelle, 1966-69 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Clark, Carr & Ellis, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Czapski, Jozef, 1964-67 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Czugunow, T. K., 1967 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - "D" General, 1958-66 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Danilov, E., 1963-69 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Dartmouth College, 1965-68, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 55)
    Includes: Department of Russian Language and Literature and Russian Review Includes letters from: John Gordon, D. von Mohrenschildt, Basil Milovsoroff, Richard Shelden, W. W. Arndt
  - Dixon, Helen, 1961-69, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - "E" General, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Elenev, N. A., 1961-66 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Erlich, Victor, 1964-67 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - "F" General, 1964-65 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Fedorova, Tat'iana, 1961-68 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    [Also spelled T. Fedorow] [Also known as Tatiana Rannit] Includes Yale University Library
  - Fesenko, T., 1967-68 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Field, Andrew, 1964-66 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Foxcroft, E. G., 1962-68 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Frank, Tat'iana Sergeevna, 1963-69 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    Includes: notations by Viktor Frank
  - Frank, Viktor Semenovich, 1959-67 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Franks, G. M., 1966-67 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - "G" General, 1965-67 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Ganfman, E. A., 1961-65, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 69)
    Includes: typescript of poems by L. P. Karsavin
  - Georges, Waldemar, 1965-66 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Giedroyc, Jerzy, 1962-68 (Box 2, Folder 71-73)
    Includes: Institut Littéraire (also known as Instytut literacki and Kultura)
  - Gibert, Michel, 1961-67 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Ginsburg, Mirra, 1963-67 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Gorbov, IAkov, 1964-67 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Grani, 1957-69 (Box 3, Folder 77-80)
    Includes: Natal'ia Borisovna Tarasova and G. Okolovich
  - Grinberg, R. N., 1960-67 (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - Guenther, Johannes von, 1963-69 (Box 3, Folder 82)
    Includes: Verlag Heinrich Ellerman
  - Gul', Roman Borisovich, 1964-68 (Box 3, Folder 83)
    Includes: letter from Philip Mosely
  - Gurevich, Naum L'vovich, 1967, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 84)
    Pseudonym: Naum Odnopozov
  - Hayward, Max, 1959-69, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Herenroth, A. S., 1964 (Box 3, Folder 86)
  - Hollerbach, Liudmila Alekseevna, 1964-69 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Hollerbach, Serge, 1961-69 (Box 3, Folder 87a)
    [Also spelled Sergei Gollerbakh] [Pseudonym: Nikolai Safonov]
    Includes notes from Liudmila Alekseevna and Andrei Andreevich Hollerbach
  - "I" General, 1967, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 88)
  - IAkamets, M. G., 1966-69 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    [Also spelled Jackamets]
  - IAnovskii, V. S., 1966-67 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - Institute for the Study of the USSR, 1965-68 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - Ioann (Shakhovskoi), Archbishop, 1963-67 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - Ionov, Alexis, Very Reverend, 1963-69 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - IUr'eva, Zoia, 1961-69, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - Ivanov, Boris Ivanovich, 1964-68 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - Ivanov, D. V., n.d. (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Ivanova, L. V. (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Ivanovskii, A. A., 1961-64 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Ivask, IUrii, 1962-69 (Box 3, Folder 98-100)
    [Also known as George Ivask]
    Includes: copies of letters from Sir Isaiah Berlin and Wilhelm Fink Verlag
  - Jakob Hegner Verlag in Köln, 1965 May 3 (Box 3, Folder 101)
    Signed by H. Jürgensmayer
  - Jankelevitch, Vladimir, 1964-66 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - "K" General, 1965-69, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 103)
  - Kandinsky, Nina, 1964-67 (Box 4, Folder 104-105)
    Includes: holograph and typescript drafts of introduction to Wassily Kandinsky's Dukhovnoe v iskusstve
  - Karpovich, Michael, 1956-58 (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Kayden, Eugene, 1962-66 (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Klenovskii, Dmitrii, 1958-69 (Box 4, Folder 108-110)
    [Pseudonym of D. I. Krachkovskii]
  - Klimov, E. E., 1961-63 (Box 4, Folder 111)
  - Kline, G. L., 1967-69 (Box 4, Folder 112)
    Includes: offprint
  - Kluge, Rolf Dieter, 1966-68 (Box 4, Folder 113)
  - Kochevitsky, George, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 114)
  - Kodjak, Andrej, 1967-69, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 115)
    [Also spelled Andrei Kodzhak]
  - Koriakov, M. M., 1965 June 29 (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Kotomkin, A., 1946 Nov 5 (Box 4, Folder 117)
    Includes: poems, typescript
  - Kovarsky, Ilia N., 1960 Jul 24 (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Kovarsky, Vera, 1954-69, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 119-121)
  - Kovarsky, Lydia (Box 4, Folder 119-121)
    Includes: one TLS from Faubion Bowers to Vera Kovarsky Some letters written on stationary of Ilia N. Kovarsky
  - Krupenskii, M., 1957-69, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 122)
    Includes: ALS to Krupenskii from E. N. Neledinskii
  - Ktorova, Alla Pavlovna, 1963-65 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - Lebedev, Fedor Tarasovich, 1958-64 (Box 4, Folder 124)
    Includes: TSentral'noe Ob"edinenie Politicheskikh Emigrantov SSSR and Svoboda
  - Lifar, Serge, 1965-67 (Box 4, Folder 125)
    [Also known as Sergei Lifar']
  - Lipson, Leon, 1966 Mar 11 (Box 4, Folder 126)
    Includes: Yale Law School
  - Lisovskii, A., 1964 (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - Litfund, 1961 Apr 26 (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - Literaturnaia gazeta, 1966, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 129)
  - Literaturnyi sovremennik, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 130)
    Includes: Boris IAkovlev
  - Lo Gatto, Ettore, 1963-68 (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - "M" General, 1964-67 (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - McVay, Gordon, 1967-69 (Box 4, Folder 133)
    Includes: R. D. B. Thomson
  - Magidoff, Robert, 1963-64 (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - Mallac, Guy de, 1963-69, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - Margolin, IUlii, 1960-69 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - Markov, Vladimir, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - Mamchenko, Viktor, 1961-69 (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - Matthias, I., 1965 (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - Mackiewicz, Jozef, 1967-69 (Box 4, Folder 140)
  - [Meier], Ol'ga Aleksandrovna, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Mil'rud, A. M., 1965-69 (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Moch, Jules, 1965-69, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - Moch, Eliane (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - Le monde, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 144)
  - Mozhaiskaia, Ol'ga, 1965-69, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - "N" General, 1965-66 (Box 5, Folder 146)
  - Nabokov, Vladimir Vladimirovich, 1966-67 (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - Nabokova, Vera (Box 5, Folder 147)
  - Narokov, Nikolai, 1961-67, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 148)
  - Nartsissov, Boris, 1961, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 149)
  - Neimirok, A., 1966-67 (Box 5, Folder 150)
  - Nidermuller, Nina, 1963-66 (Box 5, Folder 151)
  - Nikitina, N., 1966-67 (Box 5, Folder 152)
  - Nikolenko, L., 1966-69 (Box 5, Folder 153)
  - Nord, Paul, 1967-68 (Box 5, Folder 154)
  - Novoe russkoe slovo, 1959-67 (Box 5, Folder 155)
  - "O" General, 1954-67 (Box 5, Folder 156)
  - Obolensky, Dimitri, 1958-62 (Box 5, Folder 157)
  - Odoevtseva, Irina Vladimirovna, 1964-65 (Box 5, Folder 158)
  - Oras, Ants, 1966-69, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 159)
  - Ozeretskovskii, G. E., 1966-67 (Box 5, Folder 160)
  - "P" General, 1965-67 (Box 5, Folder 161)
  - PEN in Exile, 1961-66 (Box 5, Folder 162)
  - Pletnev, Rostislav, 1961-69, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 163-165)
    Includes: "Zametki o slavianovedenii", typescript
  - Polevaia, O., 1964-67 (Box 5, Folder 166)
  - Polivanov, M. P., 1963-65, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 167)
  - Poltoratskii, N. P., 1964-66 (Box 5, Folder 168)
  - Popov, Igor' Vsevolodovich, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 169)
  - Popova, V., 1966-69, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 170)
  - Lazareva, N. (Box 5, Folder 170)
  - Poppe, N. N., 1962-69 (Box 5, Folder 171)
  - Pregel', Sofiia, 1962-67 (Box 5, Folder 172)
  - Proyart, Jacqueline de, 1962-67 (Box 5, Folder 173)
  - "R" General, 1957-69, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 174)
  - Radaskaus, Henrikas, 1965-67 (Box 5, Folder 175)
  - Rafal'skii, Sergei, 1961-67, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 176)
  - Rais, Emmanuil, 1961-69 (Box 5, Folder 177-182)
    Includes: Pod glukhimi nebesami, page-proofs and typescript fragment, and various typescripts by Rais
  - Rannit, Aleksis, 1961-69 (Box 6, Folder 183-187)
    Includes: Yale University Library Includes: copies of letters from Lidiia Alekseeva, N. N. Berberova, and Gleb Struve, Rannit's correspondence with Francis Brown ( The New York Times Book Review ), clippings, holograph and typescript poems, programs, and booklet The Current State of Baltic Literatures under Soviet Occupation
    See also: Box 13, folder 367
  - Rannit, Tatiana
    See: Tat'iana Fedorova, box 2, folder 61
  - Reavey, George, 1962, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 188)
  - Redlich, R., 1966-67 (Box 6, Folder 189)
  - Reilly, Alayne P., 1964-65 (Box 6, Folder 190)
  - Richerche Slavistiche (Box 6, Folder 191)
    Includes: Riccardo Picchio and E. Gasparini
  - Rimarenko, Adrian, Very Reverend, 1966 Dec 30 (Box 6, Folder 192)
  - Rosimov, G., 1961-67 (Box 6, Folder 193)
    Pseudonym of IUrii Viktorovich Ofrosimov
  - Russian-American Club of Syracuse, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 194)
  - Rzhevskii, Leonid Denisovich, 1961-68, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 195)
  - "S" General, 1965-67 (Box 6, Folder 196)
  - Samarin, Vladimir, 1961-69 (Box 6, Folder 197-204)
    Pseudonym of Vladimir Dmitrievich Sokolov Includes: Teni na stene: rasskazy, bound typescript
  - Samilov, Mikhail, 1956-66 (Box 6, Folder 205)
  - Samilov, Ol'ga (Box 6, Folder 205)
  - Savin, D., 1966 (Box 6, Folder 206)
  - Schakovskoy, Zinaida, Princess, 1963-69, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 207)
    [Also known as Zinaida Alekseevna Shakhovskaia] Includes La pensée russe
  - Seduro, Vladimir Il'ich, 1965-68 (Box 6, Folder 208)
    Also known as Uladzimer Hlybinny
  - Sedykh, Andrei, 1965-67 (Box 6, Folder 209)
    [Pseudonym of IAkov Moiseevich TSvibak]
  - Shimanskaia, Aglaida, 1963-66 (Box 6, Folder 210)
  - Shiriaeva, N. I., 1962-66 (Box 6, Folder 211)
  - Shkurko, V. P., 1961 (Box 6, Folder 212)
  - Shor, Ol'ga Aleksandrovna, 1964-69 (Box 6, Folder 213)
    Includes: D. V. Ivanov
  - Shvarts, S. M., 1961-65 (Box 6, Folder 214)
  - Stammler, Heinrich A., 1965-69, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 215-216)
    [Also known as: Andrei Vladimirovich Shtammler]
    Includes: University of Kansas, Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures, and J. Conrad
  - Struve, Aleksei Petrovich, 1964-66 (Box 6, Folder 217)
  - Struve, Gleb
    Includes: typescripts, copies, photostats relating to the editing of the collected works of Boris Pasternak, Anna Akhmatova, Osip Mandel'shtam, Nikolai Gumilev, Nikolai Kliuev
    - Letters, 1952-63 (Box 7, Folder 218-231)
    - Letters, 1964-65 (Box 8, Folder 232-244)
    - Letters, 1965-69 (Box 9, Folder 245-255)
  - Struve, N. A., 1962-69 (Box 9, Folder 256-257)
  - Sumbatov, V. A., 1960-69 (Box 9, Folder 258)
  - Sven-Kulbnitzky, V., 1965 (Box 9, Folder 259)
  - "T" General, 1964-69 (Box 10, Folder 260)
  - Taranovski, Kiril, 1968-69 (Box 10, Folder 261)
  - Tauber, Ekaterina, 1962-68 (Box 10, Folder 262)
  - Terapiano, IUrii, 1957-67 (Box 10, Folder 263-266)
    Includes: clippings
  - Terras, Victor, 1966-69 (Box 10, Folder 267)
    Includes: Slavic and East European Journal
  - Teterevnikov, N., 1968 (Box 10, Folder 268)
  - Trotskaia, Zinaida, 1964-65 (Box 10, Folder 269)
  - Tschizewskij, Dmitrij, 1962-67, n.d. (Box 10, Folder 270)
    [Also spelled: Chizhevskii, Chyzhev'skyi]
  - Tyrkova-Williams, Ariadna, 1960 Aug 6 (Box 10, Folder 271)
    [Also spelled Tyrkova-Vil'iams]
  - "U" General, 1953-67 (Box 10, Folder 272)
  - Ul'ianov, N., 1962-69 (Box 10, Folder 273)
  - Under, Marie, 1966-68 (Box 10, Folder 274)
  - "V" General, 1966 (Box 10, Folder 275)